Dusty Edward Werth

Lee's Summit, MO • dusty.werth@outlook.com • 816-551-7575 • dustywerth.github.io

SKILLS

Languages: Python, SQL, VBA, Bicep, Arcade

Data Visualization: Power BI, Experience Builder Dashboards (ArcGIS Online), Microsoft Excel

Cloud Platform: Microsoft Azure

Data Analysis: ArcGIS Model Builder, Feature Manipulation Engine (ETL Software), Power BI

Data Modeling, Microsoft Excel (Advanced Functions, Custom Functions, Macros)

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Associate Environmental Scientist with 17+ years of GIS and consulting experience. Specializing in process mapping and developing tools to increase efficiency and quality. Leading and organizing teams to take on multiple projects simultaneously while providing effective communication with stakeholders ranging from new hires to Global Practice leadership.

EXPERIENCE

Associate Environmental Scientist | Burns & McDonnell

Jan. 2023 – Present

- Implemented the first Spark program in the company's history to find and recognize employee-owners who have implemented innovations on active projects
- Developed and implemented a training program that resulted in approximately 1,300 person-hours of training
- Implemented numerous process improvements that are estimated to save over 5,500 hours in 2024
- Implemented a data governance program to increase efficiency and quality for all aspects of the GIS program
- Directed the software license review resulting in a savings of approximately \$250k per year
- Managed the development of the new fully web-based version of the RAPID Application
- Developed Infrastructure as Code to deploy Azure environments (Bicep)
- Implemented and Maintained FME Flow application and servers

Senior Environmental Scientist | Burns & McDonnell

Jan. 2014 - Dec. 2022

- Served as an assistant project manager as well as principal investigator on numerous projects primarily focused on the Electric Utility and Renewables Market Sectors
- Developed numerous tools to decrease active time on projects and increase quality
- Developed the first iteration of RAPID Application
- Supported the development of the custom Envolve Software
- Oversaw the transition of the Envolve software from the external vendor to our BMI team
- Developed the Data Model for Envolve to allow for accurate reporting via Power BI
- Implemented the first Ignite program in the Environmental Services Global Practice history
- Developed numerous training programs and classes for the Environmental Services Global Practice
- Assembled a team of developers to support the custom software needs of Environmental Services Global Practice
- Worked with IT on numerous initiatives

Dusty Edward Werth

Lee's Summit, MO • dusty.werth@outlook.com • 816-551-7575 • dustywerth.github.io

Staff Environmental Scientist | Burns & McDonnell

Jan. 2010 - Dec. 2013

- Served as Principal Investigator on routing and siting studies
- Began the ENS GIS practice by teaching myself the software and presenting the value of having internal staff to do the work
- Began the Aeronautical Obstruction Evaluation team to evaluate projects for impacts prior to submitting to the FAA
- Created the ENS Cost Estimating tool that is currently used to estimate every project proposal for ENS
- Architected the Route Analysis tools used on routing and siting studies today
- Served as the IT Coordinator for the ES&P Global Practice

Assistant Environmental Scientist | Burns & McDonnell

June 2006 - Dec. 2009

- Assisted project managers on routing and siting studies, environmental assessments, categorical exclusions, and environmental impact studies
- Developed applications to increase quality and decrease time for data analysis in routing and siting studies

EXPERTISE

- Process Mapping and Improvement
- Workflow Creation and Optimization
- Data Conversion and Integration
- Data Modeling and Visualization

GENERAL

Application development

Agile Waterfall DevOps CI/CD

User experience testing

Process mapping and improvement

Requirements gathering

Software testing
Systems integration
Workflow design
Data Modeling
Database design

SOFTWARE

Feature Manipulation Engine (FME)

Microsoft SQL Server

ArcGIS Desktop

ArcPro/ArcMap/ArcCatalog

ArcGIS Online (AGOL)

Microsoft Windows Server

Microsoft Office

Microsoft Project

Power BI

UiPath

Visual Studio Code

Github

Microsoft SQL Server Management

Studio (SSMS)

Fiddler

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science – Biology | Avila University 2006